בוקר טוב. Boker Tov.
So today's דף daf is נח nun chet and we pick up
at the very bottom of נז עמוד ב. nun zayin amud bet.
So as we were saying at the end of yesterday,
well let's take a look, let's do it from the two dots,
okay? So about eight lines from the bottom of נז עמוד ב.
nun zayin amud bet. אם דמה פר לתוך דם השעיר. im dama
par letoch dam hase'ir. תנן tnan now
so now we have done the seven sprinklings, one and seven on
the inside, one and seven on the outside towards the פרוכת, parochet,
not on the פרוכת, parochet, although there was an opinion that it
was directed on the פרוכת, parochet, but towards the פרוכת. parochet. And
now we're going to the מזבח הזהב, mizbeach hazahav, the golden altar,
and there you're going to put on the four corners and seven
on the top. So just contrast this by the way, an issue
we discussed yesterday also comparing it to certain types of קרבנות korbonot
that are brought inside the היכל, heichal, like the פר העלם דבר
של ציבור, par he'elam davar shel tzibur, the ox brought when the
entire people sin based on a ruling of the בית דין. beis
din.
So there it says you do seven on the פרוכת parochet as
opposed to here it was one and seven. That was a point
that was made by the תוספות ישנים. Tosafos Yeshanim. By the way
the תוס׳ Tos here by the יום כיפור Yom Kippur is not
clear that you do it on the פרוכת parochet or what you
do it on the פרוכת parochet but presumably we learn from that
model and we learn because that's our interpretation of וכן יעשה לאהל
מועד. vechein ya'aseh le'ohel moed. So you do one and seven on
the פרוכת parochet as opposed to a normal thing that was done
on the inside would be seven. And then here you're going to
do on the four corners and seven on the top where a
normal one that was done on the inside you would just do
the four corners, not the seven on the top. Now when you
are doing the ones on the פרוכת parochet the פסוקים psukim say
the פסוקים psukim say it says right when it says you do
on the כפורת kaporet it says first it says you do the
פר par then it says ושחט את השעיר והביא את דמו מבית
לפרוכת ועשה את דמו כאשר עשה לדם הפר. veshachat es hase'ir vehevi
es damo mi'beis laparochet ve'asah es damo ka'asher asah ledam hapar. So
that's clearly the פר par and the שעיר se'ir are separate. You
even שחט shacht the שעיר se'ir after the פר. par. Then it
says וכן יעשה לאהל מועד vechein ya'aseh le'ohel moed which is the
same one and seven on the inside, one and seven on the
outside, the same way they're separate on the inside, they're separate on
the outside on the פרוכת, parochet, although the גמרא Gemara dealt with
what happens בדיעבד bedi'avad if they get mixed up. Now the question
is going to be what happens by the מזבח. mizbeach. So the
פסוק posuk says ויצא אל המזבח אשר לפני ה׳ וכיפר עליו ולקח
מדם הפר ומדם השעיר ונתן על קרנות המזבח סביב. veyatzah el hamizbeach
asher lifnei Hashem vechiper alav velakach midam hapar umidam hase'ir venasan al
karnot hamizbeach saviv.
And the question is what does that mean? At this stage are
you taking from them both combined, mixed together, or are you doing
one thing from the דם הפר dam hapar and a separate thing
from the דם השעיר? dam hase'ir? Then it says והזה עליו מן
הדם באצבעו שבע פעמים. vehizah alav min hadam be'etzba'o sheva pe'amim. So
when it says finally the seven times, it's מן הדם. min hadam.
So at that stage there's no question they're mixed together. When it
says the seven times it says you take מן הדם. min hadam.
So there's only one blood, they're mixed together. But how about when
you're doing it on the corners? מדם הפר ומדם השעיר. midam hapar
umidam hase'ir.
Is that the two of them mixed or is that each one
separately? And that is the debate we're about to see. Our משנה
Mishnah says you mix them but we're about to see that even
before the corner even for the sake of the corners
we are about to see that's a debate. So let's take a
look. תנן tnan our משנה Mishnah goes כמאן דאמר מערבין לקרנות. keman
de'amar me'arvin lekrannot. Not only would they be mixed for the seven
on the top which we're going to get to but even for
the corners. איתמר it'mar רב יאשיה ורב יונתן. Rav Yoshiya veRav Yonasan.
חד אמר מערבין chad amar me'arvin
one says you mix them וחד אמר אין מערבין vechad amar ein
me'arvin you don't. תסתיים דרב יאשיה הוא דאמר מערבין. tistayem deRav Yoshiya
hu de'amar me'arvin. רב יאשיה Rav Yoshiya will be the one that
says that you combine them for the corners. דאמר de'amar because we
know elsewhere in general questions of interpreting the פסוקים psukim רב יאשיה
Rav Yoshiya says אף על גב דלא כתיב יחדיו כמאן דכתיב יחדיו
דמי. af al gav delo ksiv yachdav keman dechsiv yachdav dami.
As we mentioned yesterday a ו vav in the תורה Torah is
often ambiguous. Does it mean and or or? So for example when
the תורה Torah says ומכה אביו ואמו מות יומת umakeh aviv ve'imo
mos yumos does it mean only after you've smitten both your father
and your mother or does it mean your father or your mother?
So clearly
sometimes it means or or it means this by itself and that
by itself and sometimes it means combined. So normally we would say
well it depends on context. But the גמרא Gemara assumes that you
have to have a default. What's your default assumption before you try
to look at clues in the context to tell you maybe it
means something different than the default? So רב יאשיה Rav Yoshiya says
the default is that it means combined. So obviously he has a
פסוק posuk from ומכה אביו ואמו umakeh aviv ve'imo to tell you
it means separate or he learns out from context and from other
clues it means separate but his default is to say it means
combined. So the again the statement is אף על גב דלא כתיב
יחדיו af al gav delo ksiv yachdav even though it doesn't explicitly
say combined כמאן דכתיב יחדיו דמי keman dechsiv yachdav dami our default
assumption is that it means combined.
So when it says the corners do you mean the corners at
the bottom of the מזבח mizbeach
or the no no no the קרנות krannot the horns fine the
horns right that's more accurate sorry the horns. Okay so he says
even though it doesn't say יחדיו yachdav it's like it does the
default is it means combined. So when it says דם הפר ודם
השעיר dam hapar vedam hase'ir it means combined already by the time
you're doing the horns of the of the altar you're combined they're
combined. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says no, אפילו תימא רבי יונתן, afilu
teima Rebbe Yonason, it could even be רבי יונתן, Rebbe Yonason, who
normally says that you assume means separate. שאני הכא דכתיב אחת. shani
hacha d'chsiv achas. It says אחת, achas, meaning where does it say
so? It's not so clear that this is directly in this context,
but after this it says וכילם לכפר את הקדש, v'chilam l'chaper es
hakodesh,
where is it? ונתן ממנו... v'nasan mimenu...
much later it says... much later...
much later...
right, it's the very end, it says והיתה זאת לכם, v'haysa zos
lachem, the very end, like 20 פסוקים psukim later, והיתה זאת לכם
לחקת עולם לכפר על בני ישראל מכל חטאתם אחת בשנה. v'haysa zos
lachem l'chukas olam l'chaper al bnei yisrael mikol chatosam achas bashana.
So somehow he says that אחת achas written much further, not clearly
in the context of this, is still saying that it's combined, and
somehow that אחת achas combines it. So that's a pretty big stretch.
But it says you could say even if normally you don't say
it means mix, maybe you get from the אחת, achas, thank you
so much, that comes much later, that it means mix. רש"י Rashi
says וכפר אהרן על קרנתיו אחת בשנה.
v'chiper aharon al karnosav
achas bashana.
Where? שמות ל'. Shemos lamed.
Oh,
thank you. That makes a little bit more sense.
Ah,
so that's by the מזבח הזהב, mizbeach hazahav, thank you Michael. By
the מזבח הזהב mizbeach hazahav in תצוה, Tetzaveh, when it's making the
מזבח הזהב, mizbeach hazahav, it says ועשית מזבח, v'asisa mizbeach, ועשית אתו
v'asisa oso לפני הפרכת אשר על
ארן העדת, lifnei haparoches
asher al aron ha'eidus, והקטיר אהרן קטרת סמים, v'hiktir aharon ktores samim,
לא תעלו עליו, lo sa'alu alav, וכפר אהרן על קרנתיו אחת בשנה
מדם חטאת הכפרים אחת בשנה
יכפר עליו לדרתיכם.
v'chiper aharon al karnosav achas bashana midam chatas hakippurim achas bashana
yichaper alav l'doroseichem.
Thank you, Michael. Yes, that's much more in the location of what
we're talking. It says there at the end of the מזבח הקטרת
mizbeach haktoret the making of it in תצוה, Tetzaveh, Aaron will atone
for it once in the year from the blood of the כפורים.
Kippurim. So the once he's saying, and it says אחת achas twice,
is saying that you combine the atonements. You do one act of
atonement. That makes a lot more sense. You do the bloods together
on the מזבח. mizbeach. So you could have learned it from there
regardless of how you normally interpret a ו, vav, whether it means
combined or separate. Okay, תניא דלא כשינויא. Tanya d'lo k'shinuyan. We taught
a ברייתא braisa not like our answer. Meaning that it's not about
the אחת, achas, it's about how you normally but that it's רבי
יאשיה, Rebbe Yoshia, his in- his normal position that ו vav means
combined. What does the ברייתא braisa say? ולקח מדם הפר ומדם השעיר,
v'lakach midam hapar umidam hase'ir, מעורבין דברי רבי יאשיה. m'uravin divrei Rebbe
Yoshia. That they should be mixed. Again, not because it says אחת,
achas, just the simple fact that it says both means mix. That's
what רבי יאשיה Rebbe Yoshia says. רבי יונתן, Rebbe Yonason, top of
נ"ח עמוד א'. nun ches amud aleph. רבי יונתן אומר לא מזה
בפני עצמו ומזה בפני עצמו. Rebbe Yonason omer no mizeh bifnei atzmo
umizeh bifnei atzmo. Exactly as we would have predicted. רבי יאשיה Rebbe
Yoshia says that it says this and this, it means combined, and
רבי יונתן Rebbe Yonason says it means separate. אמר לו רבי יאשיה.
amar lo Rebbe Yoshia. So רבי יאשיה Rebbe Yoshia said to רבי
יונתן: Rebbe Yonason: הלא כבר נאמר אחת. halo kvar ne'emar achas. So
now רבי יאשיה Rebbe Yoshia is saying the way the גמרא Gemara
would read it is, look, according to me just the fact that
it says A and B means combined. You, who normally don't think
A and B means combined, but it says over there in תצוה,
Tetzaveh, it says once, one atonement, so you obviously do it once,
not twice. אמר לו רבי יונתן. amar lo Rebbe Yonason. רבי יונתן
Rebbe Yonason said back to him: הלא כבר נאמר מדם הפר ומדם
השעיר. halo kvar ne'emar midam hapar umidam hase'ir. No,
'cause if it wanted to say one it would have said מדם
הפר והשעיר. midam hapar v'hase'ir. Since it says מדם הפר ומדם השעיר,
midam hapar umidam hase'ir,
that's to say מדם הפר dam hapar is separate and מדם השעיר
dam hase'ir separate. So actually I read from the פסוק, pasuk, not
just normally I read a ו vav as not meaning combined, but
the fact that it says separately מדם הפר ומדם השעיר midam hapar
umidam hase'ir
means separate. Okay, אם כן למה נאמר אחת? im kein lama ne'emar
achas? So what do I do, you're insisting it says one atonement
means you combine them and you do one atonement? No. Right.
למה לך אחת ולא שתים מדם הפר אחת ולא שתים מדם השעיר.
lama lach achas v'lo shtayim midam hapar achas v'lo shtayim midam hase'ir.
It means you don't do it twice from the blood of the
ox, and you don't do it twice from the blood of the
שעיר. se'ir. Each blood you do only once, but you don't- not
that you do all the bloods combined in one act. Okay, תניא
אידך. tanya idach. We done another ברייתא. braisa. ולקח מדם הפר ומדם
השעיר, v'lakach midam hapar umidam hase'ir, שמעורבין זה בזה. shem'uravin zeh b'zeh.
Okay, again רבי יאשיה, Rebbe Yoshia, מדם הפר
ומדם השעיר, midam hapar umidam hase'ir, A and B means you mix
them together. אתה אומר שמעורבין זה בזה או אינו אלא מזה בפני
עצמו ומזה בפני עצמו? atah omer shem'uravin zeh b'zeh o eino ela
mizeh bifnei atzmo v'mizeh bifnei atzmo? Maybe it means A by itself
and then B by itself, especially as we said it says the
word מדם midam a second time? תלמוד לומר
אחת. talmud lomar achas. No, because if you had any doubt, it
also says אחת achas at the end of תצוה, Tetzaveh, which we're
interpreting to mean again not just once in the year but one
atonement. בסתמא כרבי יאשיה. bistama k'Rebbe Yoshia. So that ברייתא braisa is
going like רבי יאשיה. Rebbe Yoshia. תוספות Tosfos points out, the fact
that it needs אחת achas might not be going like רבי יאשיה.
Rebbe Yoshia. רבי יאשיה Rebbe Yoshia could have done it just with
the ו, vav, but the end of the day, the opinion there
that you... that you mix them together, that's the רבי יאשיה Rebbi
Yoshiya opinion as we've seen. So there're two reasons to say you
mix them together. One, how you normally interpret a ו. vav. And
number two, the fact that it says once, it says the word
once twice over there at the end of תצוה Tetzaveh to underscore
one act of atonement and that's יאשיה. Yoshiya. But there still is
the position of רבי יונתן Rebbi Yonasan that you only mix it
when you get to the top. When you're doing the horns, you
are doing them separately. Yes.
Is רבי יאשיה Rebbi Yoshiya attributed as the מסדר mesader of ברייתות?
beraisos? תוספתא? Tosefta?
רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya and רבי יאשיה. Rebbi Yoshiya. No, רבי יאשיה
Rebbi Yoshiya is
attributed as the מסדר mesader of something.
תוספתא Tosefta or the ברייתא.
beraisa. כל בי דלא תנא בי רבי חייא בי רבי יאשיה, kol
bei d'lo tana bei Rebbi Chiya bei Rebbi Yoshiya, no, isn't it?
רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya and רבי יאשיה Rebbi Yoshiya are the ברייתות,
beraisos, are the תוספתא. Tosefta.
It's interesting that you got a series of ברייתות beraisos and רבי
יאשיה. Rebbi Yoshiya. Yeah, that's all. And they're arguing over who...
yeah, I think it's רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya and רבי יאשיה Rebbi
Yoshiya that are I think מסדרי תוספתא mesadrei Tosefta and the ברייתות.
beraisos. Yeah, I can double check but I'm pretty sure, yeah. Okay.
So נתן את המלא בריקן. nassan es hamalei b'reikan. Now you've mixed
the two together.
You pour the... now it's quite interesting actually because remember the blood
of the ox is bigger, so I would have imagined it's more,
more
quantity. So it says if you remember the language says עירב דם
הפר בתוך דם השעיר, eirev dam hapar l'soch dam hasair, you pour
the blood of the ox into the one of the goat. If
anything I would have thought you pour the one that's smaller quantity
into the one that's larger quantity just for the issues of spillage
and all those types of issues. But the last thing you did
was the goat. You did the goat at the פרוכת, paroches, right
in front of the פרוכת. paroches. So that's the one you're holding.
So you pick up the דם הפר dam hapar and you pour
it into it. Although still I would have said you pick this
up and then... anyway but that's the way the משנה Mishnah had
it. So it must be that even if there's a greater quantity,
even if the goat is lesser quantity, the size of the bowls
must have been similar.
The same size bowls?
Well they must have been similar because if you're mixing them they
must have actually been big enough to accommodate both because you're mixing
them. So anyway so you last did the שעיר. sair. You take
the פר par off of the pedestal, you pour it into the
goat blood and then it says, then it says you reverse it
like when you mix things well. You pour one, you know, like
somebody said like two glasses, right? You pour it that way, okay.
So right, Jonathan? I've never lifted such a bowl with one hand.
I have no idea.
Not with the פר'ס par's blood.
Look, it would make a lot more sense if you didn't say
you caught all of the blood, but the fact that we've been
assuming you catch all the blood makes it harder to envision. נתן
את המלא בריקן. nassan es hamalei b'reikan. Anyway after you're done, after
you pour the ox into the goat, then you pour what's full
into the empty, the mixture back into the empty. So בעי מיניה
רמי בר חמא מרב חסדה. ba'ei minei Rami bar Chama me'Rav Chisda.
Rami bar Chama asked Rav Chisda, and you'll see how this will
tie in. הניח מזרק בתוך מזרק וקיבל בו את הדם. hiniach mizrak
b'soch mizrak v'kibel bo es hadam. In a normal case, forget יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, you put one receiving bowl into another and you
use that for the act of קבלת הדם. kabalas hadam. So you
had a bowl inside of a bowl and the animal was שחט
shachted and the blood came out and you caught it in the
inner bowl, but you were holding the outer bowl. You were holding
like one was fit into the other. So what do you do?
I mean what's the הלכה? halacha? מהו? mahu? מין במינו חוצץ. min
b'mino chotzetz. Do we say a one type and its own type
will still be a division? It's a bowl and a bowl but
nevertheless that's an obstruction and a division and therefore you're not considered
to be touching and holding the bowl, and the כהן Kohen has
to hold the bowl. או אינו חוצץ. o eino chotzetz. Or maybe
it's not a חציצה. chatzitzah. אמר ליה. amar lei. He said to
him, תניתונה. tenisona. We taught it in our משנה. Mishnah. נתן את
המלא בריקן. nassan es hamalei b'reikan.
You put the full one in the empty one. So he understood
what that meant was not what we said. מאי לאו הושיט מזרק
מלא לתוך מזרק ריקן. mai lav hoshit mizrak malei l'soch mizrak reikan.
What it meant is you took the full bowl and you put
it into, not you poured the content, you put the full bowl
into the empty bowl. Now that would be bizarre. What would be
the point? I mean okay, you can read the משנה Mishnah that
way but why would you bother doing that? Why all of a
sudden you want to hold two bowls? Anyway that's what he thought
it meant and then you're going to go and you're going to
you know put it on the altar. So it's an עבודה avodah
that you have to be holding the bowl and so presumably there's
no difference whether you're catching the blood or placing the blood and
you can be holding it through an through another bowl in the
way. So מאי לאו mai lav does it not mean הושיט מזרק
מלא לתוך מזרק ריקן? hoshit mizrak malei l'soch mizrak reikan? You put
the full bowl into the empty bowl. לא. lo. No, that's not
what it means. It means עירה מזרק מלא לתוך מזרק ריקן. eira
mizrak malei l'soch mizrak reikan. So you poured the full bowl into
the empty bowl. So the גמרא Gemara says, התם מרישא. hatam mei'reisha.
We already got you mixing it. עירב דם הפר בתוך דם השעיר.
eirev dam hapar l'soch dam hasair. You poured the blood of the
cow of the ox into that of the goat. No, כדי לערב
יפה יפה. k'dei l'arbev yafeh yafeh. You want to pour it back
into the empty bowl to mix them well, which is clearly the
פשט pshat of the משנה. Mishnah. Otherwise as Michael said, what would
be the point even if it meant to put the full one?
Okay, so that's why we're discussing this because it was a possible
read of our משנה, Mishnah, but now that we're discussing it we're
going to focus on this question. Can you have one bowl in
another bowl? Do we say מין במינו... חוצץ min b'mino chotzetz or
not? So let's take a look. It says תא שמע, ta shma,
come and hear. היה
עומד על גבי כלי
haya omed
al gabi kli or כלי, keli, if a כהן kohen was standing
on a vessel, this is a normal case, normal day, doing the
עבודה, avoda, but he's not standing directly on the floor. And he
would normally be barefoot on the floor. And the idea is that
the same way, you know, that the floor of the מקדש Mikdash
sort of imparts sanctity, you know, it has to also he has
to be connected to the floor as well. The same way we
also need the body, the person of the כהן, kohen, the body
of the כהן kohen to be touching the vessels. All these are
seen as like pipes of, you know, כלי שרת. klei sharet. By
the way, the whole idea, you know, nowadays you talk about like
a rabbinic staff of a שול, shul, you know, you talk about
them as the כלי קודש, klei kodesh, right? So that idea, look,
a lot of this is in the תורה Torah already, when the
תורה Torah speaks about, you know, you go through this whole process
of sanctifying the כלים kelim in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, right through these קרבנות korbanot and the
sprinkling and the שמן המשחה, shemen hamishcha, and you also then sanctify
the כהנים. kohanim. So the idea is that their bodies also becomes
a type of a כלי שרת. klei sharet. So the same way,
so therefore you have to be, it's about also what is their
where's their body physically is directly in contact with. So their body
has to be in contact with the floor, and their body has
to directly be in contact with the כלי שרת klei sharet and
with the, you know, with the other things that they are using.
And that's why there's an issue of חציצה. chatzitza. So it says
היה עומד על גבי כלי, haya omed al gabi kli, if he
was not standing directly on the floor, but he was standing on
a vessel that was between him and the floor, או על גבי
רגל חבירו, o al gabi regel chaveiro, or on his friend's foot,
okay, one foot on the other, פסול, pasul, and he was doing
the עבודה, avoda, it's invalid because he was not directly touching the
floor. So that seems to be a proof that מין במינו חוצץ
min b'mino chotzetz? because it's his foot and his friend's foot and
it's considered to be an obstruction even though they're both feet, they're
both, you know, body. So the גמרא Gemara says don't you see
there מין במינו min b'mino... חוצץ? chotzetz So the גמרא Gemara says
no, שאני רגל דלא מצי מבטל ליה. shani regel d'lo matzi mevatel
lei. No, a foot is different because you cannot annul it. What
does it mean to annul it? It's like the guy says, look,
I excuse me, I'm going to need my foot here. You cannot,
you can't basically control the other guy's foot and keep it there
for as long as you want it. So therefore its ability to
be considered to be like, you know, like like well, okay, there's
a question about what מבטל ליה mevatel lei means. In general, I
mean not what it means but the significance. In general there's a
question about a
חציצה, chatzitza, right? What is the concern, I mean how do you
conceptualize the idea of a חציצה? chatzitza? Because I'll give you I'll
give you an example, you know, where this plays out. The הלכה
halacha is, if you're not מקפיד makpid of something on your body,
then it's not חוצץ. chotzetz. I've got this thing on my body,
but you know, I don't mind that it's here. So okay fine,
then it's not a חציצה. chatzitza. Why is that? It's still preventing,
I mean the most normal case is when you go to the
מקוה. mikvah. It's still preventing water to get on your body. Why
just because you don't care that it's there that you're not מקפיד
makpid is it not a חציצה? chatzitza?
What do you mean a thing on your body, a scab?
Yeah, or let's say let's say a band-aid. Yeah, a band-aid, okay?
I want it there, right, perfect example, that's why I have it
on. I want it there, I don't want it off, so it's
not a חציצה. chatzitza. Okay, why is that? So there's two explanations.
One is that it's not enough that it prevents the water from
getting on your body. To be defined as a חציצה chatzitza it
has to sort of actively an identity as a foreign body, as
an obstruction and a foreign body. So even though in practice this
is preventing water from getting on my body, it's not a foreign
body because it's only foreign if I actively don't want it there.
If I don't care if it's there or not, it's not considered
a foreign body. That's one idea, that it has to be labeled
a חציצה. chatzitza. The other idea goes in the opposite direction and
says no, actually it's a problem, water's not getting on your body,
but if you don't mind then it becomes considered like טפל tafel
secondary to your body. It becomes considered like part of your body.
And therefore even though water doesn't get on your body, it only
gets on the band-aid, but the band-aid now is part of your
body. Now there's a huge gap between those because this is one
says it's only a problem when it's actively defined as a חציצה.
chatzitza. The other says until you can define it as part of
your body, okay, then it's going to be a problem. So the
difference is the whole huge middle scenario, right, that I don't want
it to actively be part of my body, I'm not defining it
as part of my body, but on the other hand I don't
actively want it off, and a lot of the debates by the
way in contemporary הלכה halacha about חציצה chatzitza have to do with
where you fall on that divide. Like a lot of people would
actually say a band-aid is a חציצה chatzitza because even though I
don't mind that it's on right now, eventually I want it off
and we can't really call it part of my body, so that's
like the debate. You have to call it part of your body
to make it okay, or do you just not have to call
it an obstruction and then it's an okay. So what's this idea
of not מבטל ליה? mevatel lei? So the easiest thing to say
מבטל ליה mevatel lei is if you by a חציצה chatzitza need
it to be considered part of your body. So here by the
כלי kli you would need it to be considered like to become
part of the כלי. kli. So I can't make your foot part
of my body. Your foot is always going to be something you're
going to want to keep to
yourself, right? Like two vessels, I can say yeah, they're combined and
it's all the same thing, it's all like it's one big thing,
like it's one big vessel. It's מין במינו, min b'mino, it's not
foreign matter, right? It's not a foreign object, it's all the same
מין, min, it's all one. But not your foot, your foot is
always going to be separate. That's the easiest way to understand it.
And לא מבטלי. lo mivatlei. But the other way is even if
you understand like the idea that is it like a foreign body,
לא מבטלי lo mivatlei could also say that. It's one thing when
it's my vessels or the בית המקדש's Beis HaMikdash vessels but nobody
minds what I'm doing with them. I could say it's not foreign,
it's not out of place, but your foot is something you're always
going to want to take away, right? So therefore it always has
a status of something foreign. And therefore even if it is מין
במינו, min bemino, it always remains a foreign thing and therefore it
remains a חציצה. chatzitzah.
Yeah, I understand how you could get other vessels, parts of vessels,
they were clearly made separately. I mean, so... Right, in some sense
temporarily you could define it as that.
Yeah. So that would be the idea, which I understand, that's actually
the harder concept. Wait, there's more reason to say that's not to
be a foreign body. It's harder to say that all the things
that aren't חציצות chatzitzos are becoming like one with the thing. רש"י...
Rashi... רש"י Rashi says גבי רגל, gabbei regel, רש"י Rashi says דלא
מבטלי חברו את רגלו עד שיגמור עבודתו. d'lo mivatlei chaveiro es raglo
ad sheyigmor avodaso. I'm not going to let you stand on my
foot until you're done doing what you need to do. I'm going
to want it back now. So therefore that's different, that will always
be a חציצה. chatzitzah. Okay, so let's go look back at the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay, איכא דאמרי, ika d'amri, some say הכא בעי, hacha
ba'ei, here is the question. דרך שירות בכך או אין דרך שירות
בכך? derech sheirus bekhach o ein derech sheirus bekhach? חציצה chatzitzah I'm
not bothered. I'm going to assume it's not a חציצה, chatzitzah, it's
all מין במינו min bemino by the one vessel in the other.
It's all the same thing, it's all considered one thing, it's not
as foreign, it's not a חציצה. chatzitzah. But the question is when
you do the עבודה, avoda, it's לעמוד לשרת. la'amod lishares. It has
to be a way of serving. And is it considered an appropriate
way to serve, you know, God or, you know, a master to
do one vessel in another vessel? So maybe the problem is in
the action, not
so much in the physical connection.
Okay, so חציצה's chatzitzah now no longer... it's assuming חציצה chatzitzah isn't
the problem and it wants to know is it a problem of
just the action of דרך שירות. derech sheirus. Okay, so דרך שירות
בכך או אין דרך שירות בכך. derech sheirus bekhach o ein derech
sheirus bekhach. Maybe that would be unique to the issue of עבודה
avoda the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. For other הלכות, halachos, מין במינו
min bemino wouldn't be a חציצה. chatzitzah. Okay, תא שמע tasha come
and hear, דתני דבי רבי ישמעאל. d'tani d'vei Rabbi Yishmael. רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael teaches את כל כלי השרת אשר ישרתו בם בקודש. es
kol klei hashareis asher yesharsu bam bakodesh. All the holy vessels that
they will serve with them in the plural in the holy. שני
כלים בם ושירות אחד אשר ישרתו, shnei kelim bam v'sheirus echad asher
yesharsu, right? They will serve with them. So as opposed to saying
multiple services, no, one service with multiple vessels. So שני כלים ושירות
אחד, shnei kelim v'sheirus echad,
so that seems to be the conclusion. A, it's not a חציצה,
chatzitzah, and B, it considers to be דרך שירות בכך, derech sheirus
bekhach, which is fascinating. You could have assumed either one was a
problem, the גמרא Gemara seems to say both are okay. So בעי
מיניה רבי בר חמא מרב חסדא. ba'ei minei Rabbi Bar Chama me'Rav
Chisda. So רבי בר חמא Rabbi Bar Chama asked רב חסדא Rav
Chisda the following question. הניח סיב בתוך המזרק וקיבל בו את הדם
מהו?
hinniach siv b'toch hamizrak
v'kibeil bo es hadam mahu? Let's say you put a sieve, a
what would you call it, if a wick not a what do
they make those wicker baskets out of? Wicker? No. What's that called?
Bast? Bast? Anyway, something like that, something like the palm, what do
you call that whole, you know, the thing that's like the thing
that anyway, palm bast. Palm bast? Bast? Anyway. Okay, okay, ah, there
you go, palm... anyway. So one of these types of a porous
material, right? A plant type of porous material. סיב siv is like
a vine that grows around the tree, right? So it's right now
it's חוצץ, chotzeitz, but if you leave the blood in long enough,
the blood will seep through, right? And that actually is also very
important הלכה halacha by חציצה, chatzitzah, something that is water permeable even
if water isn't getting through right away. One of the hardest questions
about חציצה chatzitzah for a מקווה mikvah is a person with an
ear infection, a woman with an ear infection because you can say
well you put in a plug and I need it there, but
how could you say that it's like an... like, you know, if
אינו מקפיד eino makpid right now, sure, you want it in your
ear right now because you need to protect your ear, whatever, but
the whole point is to keep the water out. So how could
you call it not a חציצה chatzitzah if its whole function is
to keep the water
out? So tough question how to deal with that. So רב עובדיה
יוסף's Rav Ovadia Yosef basic approach is that even so, even though
the purpose is to keep it out, since you need it now
and you need it for a health purpose at this phase, right
now it's considered part of your body. רב משה Rav Moshe basically
talks about sort of putting like coating a cotton thing with Vaseline
and putting it in your ear and that the Vaseline will sort
of that will keep it tight. But he says but because it's
cotton and eventually if you were in long enough the water could
eventually get through the Vaseline and permeate, and therefore since it's theoretically
possible for it to be water permeable even though now the water
is not getting through, that, you know, that would be a reason...
he has other חשבונות cheshbonos as well. But the idea of using
something that's water permeable even if right now the water isn't getting
through makes it, you know, it's something that we'd say it's not
a חציצה chatzitzah problem. And that's exactly the question as well. You
put something that's אינו מינו, eino mino, you put this type of
a bast or whatever, this permeable thing in the base, the blood
doesn't hit the actual base of the כלי, kli, but if you
leave it long enough it'll seep through. Is that a חציצה chatzitzah
or not? So הניח סיב בתוך המזרק וקיבל בו את הדם מהו?
hinich siv betoch hamizrak vekibel bo et hadam mahu? מין בשאינו מינו
חוצץ min beshe'eino mino chotzetz because it's something different, it's חוצץ, chotzetz,
או אינו חוצץ o eino chotzetz or not? כיון דמחלחל לא חייץ.
kevan demachalchel lo chayitz.
And now we're going to spell this out: since it is מחלחל,
machalchel, it is porous, and the blood will eventually seep through, it's
not חוצץ. chotzetz. או דלמא לא שנא, o dilma lo shena, maybe
it doesn't matter, right now the blood has to hit the vessel.
אמר ליה, amar lei, he said to him, תנינה, tenina, we talk
זו משנה zo mishnah by פרה אדומה, parah adumah, זולף והולך עד
שהגיע לספוג. zolef veholech ad shehigia lisfog. If you dropped a sponge
into the water of the פרה אדומה, parah adumah, then you can't
use the water that's in the sponge. The water that's in the
sponge is not touching
the bottom of the vessel and it's not water yet, it's absorbed
in the sponge.
But you skip down, well
presumably, I don't know, but anyway, but you can use the rest
of the water that's in the vessel. Now why can you use
the rest of the water that's in the vessel? Some of that
water is on top of the sponge and it hasn't touched the
base of the vessel, so why can you use it? So it
says, one
minute, the גמרא gemara says like this, אמר, amar, so שאני מיא
דקלישי, shani maya deklishi, no, that's different, water is
very thin, very
non-viscous. So water will easily seep through something, so therefore we agree
to the principle of porous. In principle porous is not a חציצה
chatzitzah if something will easily seep through it. But if it will
only go over a long period of time, it's very viscous and
it'll only come after a long period of time, maybe that is
considered a חציצה. chatzitzah. So we're not sure, basically we agree to
the principle, the question is one of degree. איכא דאמרי, ika de'amri,
others say, הכי פשיטא ליה. hachi pashita lei. No, actually he did
conclude, בדם כשר, bedam kasher, if you want to use this for
blood it's fine because the blood will seep through eventually. בקומץ פסול,
bekometz pasul,
but if you have your vessel lined with this palm branch, whatever,
this palm
leaf, and you put it for the handful for the מנחה, minchah,
that's no good, because that's a solid, so for solids it is
a חציצה. chatzitzah. For liquids it's not, since eventually it will get
through, it is not considered, and again this is a very important
principle by הלכות חציצה, hilchos chatzitzah, that something that is water permeable,
even if the water won't get through immediately, is not considered to
be a חציצה chatzitzah since eventually it could get through.
I thought someone was saying you can't prove it from the water
because water is.
You can't prove it from water, but the end of the decision
was actually we're fine, the blood and water will be the same,
it's a liquid, eventually it'll get through. So the גמרא gemara concludes
very leniently. A, that this isn't a חציצה. chatzitzah. B, מין במינו
min bemino isn't a חציצה. chatzitzah. C, not only that but even
דרך שירות בכך, derech sheirus bekach, it's not considered a problem in
the act of שירות. sheirus. Now תוספות tosafos asks on this, I
want to just point out an important idea, that there's a גמרא
gemara in סוכה sukkah
that talks about what happens if I make a handle on my,
I use
a handkerchief to make a handle for my לולב. lulav. And I
stick my לולב lulav in it in this handle that I've made
and I hold my לולב lulav like that. So the גמרא gemara
wants to know maybe that's not a חציצה, chatzitzah, because
this is like לקיחה על ידי דבר אחר, lekichah al yedei davar
acher, I'm taking it via something else. So that's also considered an
act of לקיחה. lekichah. By the way, the reason we make the
whole accordion thingies or whatever is because it's all out of the
לולב lulav things, so it's מין במינו. min bemino. But the גמרא
gemara there suggests that that would not be a problem. So תוספות
tosafos says, so why here do we have this whole issue, why
isn't it just לקיחה על ידי דבר אחר? lekichah al yedei davar
acher? So תוספות tosafos says, well maybe it makes a difference, am
I using the thing as a handle or am I actually trying
to hold the thing but something is in the way? So he
says for example if here, could I use this for a second?
If this were my vessel and this were the vessel in the
vessel, if I was holding it like this, that would be לקיחה
על ידי דבר אחר. lekichah al yedei davar acher. I'm just using
the outer vessel as a handle and then that should be okay.
The problem is that when I hold it like this I'm really
it's the same act I would be doing if the vessel was
directly in my hand and now something is interfering. So how you
hold it is it לקיחה על ידי דבר אחר lekichah al yedei
davar acher or is it trying to take the thing but something
else is in the way? That's one difference. But then he says
a very important other difference. לקיחה על ידי דבר אחר lekichah al
yedei davar acher is describing the act. The תורה torah when it
says by taking the לולב, lulav, it says ולקחתם לכם. ulekachtem lachem.
It never says your hand has to touch the לולב. lulav. It
says ולקחתם לכם. ulekachtem lachem. What does it mean to take something?
Does it mean to directly touch it, or maybe if I take
it through with a handle I'm also taking it? So maybe it's
not a משום חציצה mishum chatzitzah at all, maybe it's just a
משום mishum of defining the act of לקיחה. lekichah. Is that a
לקיחה? lekichah? Am I taking something when it's in its case? Maybe
not. But maybe yes when it's in a handle. But there conceptually
it's only about the act, like when the גמרא gemara moved out
to say it's about considered the act. By serving in the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it's more than just the act of שירות sheirus
and the act of taking the blood, it's the idea of the
physical contact and that's more of an issue of חציצה chatzitza than
just an issue of an act. So if you look at the
last line of תוספות מין במינו, Tosfos min bemino, he says like
this, it says, or two lines from the bottom, where the ריצב"א
תירץ, Ritzba tiraitz, first word is תירץ. tiraitz. דבשמעתא גבי כלי שרת
מין בשאינו מינו חוצץ בכל עניין, D'bishmaisa gabei kly shares min besheino
mino chotzetz bechol inyan, even if you took it through like another,
you know, לקיחה ידי דבר אחר, lakicha yedei davar acher, you used
it as a handle. Why? דאפילו אם תמצא לומר דגבי לולב יש
חילוק כדפירושית, dafilu im timtza lomar degabei lulav yesh chilluk k'difirashis, even
if a handle is okay by לולב, lulav, it's taking it through
something, גבי כלי שרת בכל עניין מין בשאינו מינו חוצץ דניהי דכי
עביד כעין בית יד gabei kly shares bechol inyan min besheino mino
chotzetz d'nihi dechi avid k'ein beis yad fine, if you make it
like a handle, מקרי לקיחה, mikrei lakicha, it's still you took it,
so you took the לולב lulav because you used it through a
handle, but גבי כלי שרת דכתיב ולקח הכהן, gabei kly shares deksiv
v'lakach hacohen, the כהן cohen must take, the point is you need
בעצמו של כהן. be'atzmo shel cohen. לא מקרי לקיחה בעצמו של כהן.
lo mikrei lakicha be'atzmo shel cohen. There the idea is the כהן
cohen has to be in contact with it. So by לולב, lulav,
it's just what constitutes an act of taking. It's taking something directly,
or can you take it with a handle? So you still said
I took it. Fine, I took it, but that's different than saying
I touched it. By the כלי שרת, kly shares, it's like you
have to directly touch the thing and therefore the question there is
much more one of חציצה chatzitza than it would be by other
things, for there there's a requirement of directly touching, like by the
מקווה, mikvah, it's your body touches the water. There issues of חציצה
chatzitza are much more heightened than they are when we require an
act of taking where, okay, חציצה chatzitza might be a problem, but
it's only a problem because it defines that maybe you didn't take,
not because there's a requirement that it be directly in contact. Interesting
if he defined himself that he had actually taken and then he
puts his hands under hers and they waved it. But he's not
actually taking it then. All right, I mean, yeah, there are some
times that the act is—that's true by the תנופה. tnufa. But let
me look at that, let me check into that. Let's take a
look now and turn to the עמוד ב amud bais and now
a bigger דף, daf, the same תוספות. Tosfos. Let's take a look.
Rabbi, as מחלחל mchalchel you translated as porous? Yeah. I was thinking
of כחחל המקום, kachchal hamakom, how do you translate it with that
word? Maybe blood pressure or pain. How do they translate it there?
I thought it meant like something can flow through, it has the
ability for something to flow through. כחחל המקום, kachchal hamakom, same, yeah,
maybe. Right, the blood flowed to it. But although תחל tachal also
means like tremble, tremble. Like גמרא Gemara defines it a line later
actually, דזולי והולך. d'zolei vaholech. In other words, whatever מחלחל mchalchel means,
it means the liquid gets through. So it's an interesting word. How
do they translate it there? Let's take a look now. That was
interesting what you say, the same as the top. Noah, porous. Well
said. ויצא אל המזבח אשר לפני ה'. V'yatzah el hamizbeach asher lifnei
Hashem. So now we talked about mixing it, but now we—and we
talked about doing the blood separate, but this משנה Mishnah on the
horns, but this משנה Mishnah is actually going to look at the
פסוק. pasuk. How do you translate? Porous. ויצא אל המזבח אשר לפני
ה' וכפר עליו V'yatzah el hamizbeach asher lifnei Hashem v'chiper alav is
what the פסוק pasuk says. Now, which מזבח mizbeach is לפני ה'?
lifnei Hashem? There are two מזבח. mizbeach. זה מזבח הזהב. Zeh mizbeach
hazahav. That's the golden altar, because אשר לפני ה' asher lifnei Hashem
means closest to the קדש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, the golden altar. And
also we know from the other cases by, you know, when you
did something that the blood was done inside the היכל Heichal that
it would be on the golden altar. התחיל מחטא ויורד. Hischil mechatei
v'yored. You would begin to put the blood on the corners, מחטא
mechatei because it's a חטאת, chatas, so the verb for making it—putting
the blood is called מחטא, mechatei, and ויורד v'yored that your finger
would move in a downward motion, and we'll discuss that. מהיכן הוא
מתחיל? Meiheichan hu maschil? Where do you begin? מקרן מזרחית צפונית, Mikeren
mizrachis tzonis, you start at the northeast, צפונית מערבית, tzonis maaravis, northwest,
מערבית דרומית, maaravis dromis, southwest, דרומית מזרחית, dromis mizrachis, southeast. מקום שהוא
מתחיל בחטאת על מזבח החיצון, Makom shehu maschil b'chatas al mizbeach hachitzon,
the place where you begin by a חטאת chatas on the outer
altar, משם היה גומר על מזבח הפנימי, misham haya gomer al mizbeach
hapnimi, that's where
you would finish on the inner altar.
So what does that mean?
It means let's
talk
for a minute about the outer altar. Right, if you remember the
outer altar, you go to the top, you turn right, which is
counter-clockwise, and you come down. So here where do you end? On
which corner? You end at the southwest corner, right? Is that clear?
Yes. This is southeast, this is... now here, where does it say
you start? מזרחית צפונית צפונית מערבית. mizrachit tzfunit tzfonit ma'aravit. So here
you also go counter-clockwise, you start here and you end here. So
מקום שהוא, makom shehu, so you end at the southeast. So it
says מקום שהוא מתחיל בחטאת המזבח החיצון,
makom shehu matchil bachatat
hamizbeach hachitzon, you start in the southeast, שם היה גומר המזבח הפנימי,
sham haya gommer hamizbeach hapnimi, okay? So you also do counter-clockwise, but
you start at this corner. Now why do you start at this
corner, right? Why wouldn't you start at one of the first ones
that you hit? So here we're going to say because it says
ויצא אל המזבח.
veyatza el hamizbeach.
So ויצא veyatza means you get completely outer from where you were,
from your zone.
You leave that zone and you're now at the outer section.
So the outer is you come out here and you start here
and then you go counter-clockwise. Actually, the outer is the southeast. Now
why, so there's going to be the opinion that the southeast is
in another place to start, so we'll see about that. We'll see
all the entrances. Alright, so we'll see all of that, we'll see
all of that. Okay, so רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, Rabbi
Eliezer says, במקומו היה עומד ומחטא. bimkomo haya omed umachatei. You would
not actually walk around the altar, but you would stand where you
were standing and it was small, it was אמה על אמה amah
al amah as it was exactly the whole size of the golden
altar was the size of a horn of the outer altar, okay?
So he says you could just stand there and do the whole
thing, you don't have to walk around. Okay, ועל כולם היה נותן
מלמטה למעלה חוץ מזו שהיתה לפניו שהיה נותן ממעלה למטה. ve'al kulam
haya nosein milmatah lemalah chutz mizo shehayta lefanav shehaya nosein mima'alah lematah.
And this is still within רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that he would
have you standing in one place. So he says on all of
them, this is to disagree with, this is like a תנא קמא
Tana Kamma that you walk around, right? But we'll see. And he
did, well, you could have said right, you'd be מתן matan and
putting, but anyway, but implicitly he is, and we'll see that in
the גמרא. Gemara. Now on all of them you would put from
top to bottom, except from this one which is in front of
you which you would, I'm sorry, all of them you put from
bottom to top מלמטה למעלה milmatah lemalah except from
this one you would put from top to bottom. What's the reason?
So basically the altar is two אמות amot high, which is about,
what's that, about three feet? So three feet apparently, I don't know,
I didn't measure, apparently higher than your normal arm height, is that
right? No. No. רש"י Rashi says it is. Or maybe, I don't
know, maybe three feet is like this table? These are two feet,
those are three feet. Whoops, way on the table. I don't know.
רש"י Rashi says that you have to be having your arm up
at an angle. Maybe people were shorter back then. Maybe there was
the corner or maybe higher by a higher, a larger cubit. So
assuming, assuming, I'm going to assume like רש"י, Rashi, he's right, because
this clearly you'd have to be like four feet, five feet, anyway,
that you have to start high up, not like this. So then
he says like this, then he says if you are close to
yourself, close here, so how would it work? He said all of
them it would be from the bottom up, but if I'm here
and I'm going from the bottom up like this, I'm trying to
do it this way, the blood is going to, or this way,
you know, if you do the bottom up, then the blood is
going to like run down. So therefore he says the one near
me I have to do the top bottom, but the ones farther
away I would do bottom up, but if I'm right near me
and my arm is angled, I mean if my arm were like
that I could do it, right? But if my arm is like
this, then the blood is going to run down. Is it the
תנא קמא Tana Kamma that he's holding the whole כלי kli with
the blood? What? What is, the blood is already in a כלי.
kli. No, no, he's holding it. No, he's holding it now. Didn't
we say? Yeah, he had them in a כלי kli temporarily when
he was switching, but now he's mixed them and he's holding it.
And it's a drip, he's going to put his finger in it.
Yeah, but you don't, but you can put your fingertip in and
do it if you're
careful, you can put your finger in. So take a look at
the רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi where it says, you're going to get
enough for four corners? So you'd dip again, okay? Let's take a
look at רש"י. Rashi. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, it's about
eight lines down in the narrow lines. לא היה מקיפו ברגלו שהרי
כולו אינו אלא אמה על אמה מרובעת וכיון שאין שלשה קרנות סמוכות
לא יכול ליתן
מלמטה למעלה. lo haya mekifo beraglo sheharei kulo eino ela amah al
amah meruba'at vekeivan she'ein shelosha keranot semuchot lo yakhol litein milmatah lemalah.
So the ones that are farther he can do from bottom up.
חוץ מזו שהוא עומד אצלה שהיא
לפניו, chutz mizo shehu omed etzlah shehi lefanav, the one that's right
in front of him, כי אי אפשר לצדד ראש אצבעותיו למטה. ki
i efshar letzaded rosh etzba'otav lematah. You can't, again, presumably if you're
going from bottom up then your palm is facing upwards, okay? And
you can't do that, אלא למעלה, ela lemalah,
because so your finger will be upwards. וצריך למשוך המתנה ממעלה למטה,
vetzarich limshokh hamatanah mima'alah lematah, because שאם מושכה מלמטה למעלה הדם זב
לתוך בית ידו, she'im moshcha milmatah lemalah hadam zav letoch beit yado,
right? So if
you're going like this, right, then the blood is going to flow
down like that. So you have to go like, now theoretically you
could do this. But רש"י Rashi is assuming that if you're going
bottom up, you're doing it like this, and top down you're going
like that. So if it's right in front of you, you're afraid
that if you do this type of a motion, the blood will
run down, so you have to do it like that. Okay, which
is why the first opinion said מחטא ויורד, mechatei veyoreid, because the
first one that says you would walk around would have you doing
it, every corner would be in front of you. You'd be directly
in front of each corner, so again the only... His sleeves were
tight around his wrist or I don't know I always assumed they
were loose. Yeah, loose then he puts his finger in his garment.
That's true. All right, okay.
והזה על טהרו של מזבח שבע פעמים, Ve'hiza al taharo shel mizbe'ach
sheva pe'amim, he sprinkled
on the purity of the altar. We'll see what that means seven
times.
Right, it says what the פסוק pasuk says, what does it say?
ולקח מדם הפר ונתן על קרנות המזבח והזה עליו מן הדם שבע
פעמים. Velakach midam hapar venatan al karnot hamizbe'ach vehiza alav min hadam
sheva pe'amim. It says you shall sprinkle on it seven times. באצבע,
Be'etzba, it doesn't say where on it. Then it says וטהרו וקדשו
מטומאות בני ישראל. Vetaharo vekidesho mitum'ot benei yisrael. So borrowing that language
of טהר, tohar, we're saying you sprinkle on the טהרו של מזבח,
taharo shel mizbe'ach, not clear what that means, we will see. ושירי
הדם היה שופך אל יסוד מערבי של מזבח החיצון. Veshirei hadam hayah
shofech el yesod maaravi shel mizbe'ach hachitzon. The rest of the blood
would be poured at the base, the western base of the outer
altar. Because you come out here, so you hit the western base
first and you pour it on the western base. Right, that's what
the פסוק pasuk says. Okay. Actually, does it say to do the
blood or we just learned it out from elsewhere? It doesn't actually,
does it say? It doesn't say here, one minute. Yeah, it doesn't
say here that you pour the blood out. But it says it
elsewhere by the inner חטאות chata'ot that you pour the blood at
the base. ושל מזבח החיצון היה שופך אל יסוד דרומי. Veshel mizbe'ach
hachitzon hayah shofech el yesod dromi. But when you had blood left
from this altar, you'd do it on the southern base because you'd
come here, you'd
come around, you'd come down, and the
base closest to you when you would come down would be the
southern base. So here you do the western base, that's what you
hit first, and here you do the southern base. אלו ואלו מתערבים
באמה. Elu ve'elu mit'arvin ba'amah. All the blood, it doesn't matter which
base you poured them in, they would all eventually mix together and
go through the funnel that was in the or the trough in
the floor of the עזרה, azarah, ויוצאין לנחל קדרון, veyotzin lenachal kidron,
it would go out to the wadi of Kidron. And that's where
the you know, that's where like the pipe, the as it were,
the sewage pipe would empty out into. ונמכרים לגננים, Venimkarim legananim, it
would be sold to farmers לזבל lezavel for use for for what
do you call it? For fertilizer because it was, you know, very
high in nutrients. ומועלין בהן, Umo'alin bahen, but until they actually paid
for it, there was still a prohibition of מעילה me'ilah because this
was sanctified blood. We will discuss that not today, but tomorrow. Okay,
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan.
ויצא אל המזבח, Veyatza el hamizbe'ach, מה תלמוד לומר? mah talmud lomar?
What does it mean to go out? אמר רבי נחמיה, Amar Rabbi
Nechemiah, לפי שמצינו בפר הבא על כל המצוות. lefi shematzinu bepar haba
al kol hamitzvot. We find by the this was one of the
other things that are done on the inside, not on יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, an ox that would be brought because everybody sinned based
on a ruling of the בית דין, beit din, שהכהן עומד חוץ
למזבח ומזה על הפרוכת בשעה שהוא מזה. shehakohen omed chutz lamizbe'ach umazeh
al haparochet besha'ah shehu mazeh. We find there that the actual sprinkling
now this is a shocker. The sprinkling when the כהן גדול kohen
gadol what when the כהן kohen does it for the פר, par,
the ox brought for כל המצוות, kol hamitzvot, he stands here and
he sprinkles seven times. Now remember, he doesn't have to hit the
פרוכת, parochet, which is a good thing, although yesterday we did have
a פלוגתא plugta of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that he did hit
the פרוכת. parochet. And if you remember, this whole thing here is
forty אמה. amah. Right, this is twenty אמה, amah, this is forty
אמה, amah, right, remember that? Right, so that's a lot and this
is towards the front, that's a long way to be trying to
get blood. According to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, I don't know how
he did it. He stands out here and he sprinkles in that
direction. Okay, so he's got to go over the מזבח, mizbe'ach, I
guess. Yeah, I mean, he does it towards, but again, other than
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, you didn't have to hit, so but okay,
so we'll see how we know that in a minute. יכול אף
זה כן? Yachol af zeh ken? Maybe this one on יום כיפור
Yom Kippur the כהן גדול kohen gadol has to stand outside the
מזבח mizbe'ach when he sprinkles on the פרוכת? parochet? תלמוד לומר, Talmud
lomar, ויצא אל המזבח. Veyatza el hamizbe'ach. No, it's after he sprinkles
on the פרוכת, parochet, then he goes outside the מזבח. mizbe'ach. היכן
היה? Heichan hayah? Where was he until this point when he was
doing the פרוכת? parochet? לפנים מן המזבח, Lifnim min hamizbe'ach, on the
inner part of the altar between the altar and the פרוכת. parochet.
And only afterwards is he ויצא, veyatza, does he go outside. So
that's discussing it from the perspective of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Now
we're going to say the same thing from the perspective of the
פר par of כל המצוות. kol hamitzvot. תניא אידך, Tanya idach, we
taught in another ברייתא. braita. לפני השם מה תלמוד לומר? Lifne Hashem
mah talmud lomar? Why does it say before God? Right, ויצא אל
המזבח אשר לפני השם. Veyatza el hamizbe'ach asher lifne Hashem. אמר רבי
נחמיה, Amar Rabbi Nechemiah, לפי שמצינו בפר ושעיר של יום הכיפורים, lefi
shematzinu bepar vesa'ir shel Yom Hakippurim, because on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
we know שהכהן עומד לפנים מן המזבח, shehakohen omed lifnim min hamizbe'ach,
he's on the inside as we said. Only after he's done is
it ויצא. veyatza. ומזה על הפרוכת בשעה שהוא מזה. Umazeh al haparochet
besha'ah shehu mazeh. So and he sprinkles on the פרוכת parochet when
he's doing that part. He's between the פרוכת parochet and the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. יכול אף זה כן? Yachol af zeh ken? Maybe it's true
also by the פר par of כל המצוות? kol hamitzvot? תלמוד לומר,
Talmud lomar, מזבח קטורת הסמים לפני השם. Mizbe'ach ketoret hasamim lifne Hashem.
מזבח לפני ה' אשר באוהל מועד. mizbeach lifnei Hashem asher b'ohel moed.
So it says, he shall sprinkle on the מזבח mizbeach of the
קטורת ketores which is before God, so מזבח לפני ה', mizbeach lifnei
Hashem, the מזבח mizbeach is before God, and the כהן kohen isn't
before God even when he does the sprinkling on the פרוכת. parochet.
כיצד, keitzad, how would it be? עומד חוץ למזבח ומזה, omeid chutz
lamizbeach u'mazzeh, he stands outside and does the sprinkling. Now the funny
thing about that is, is that that's what it says when he
gets to the מזבח, mizbeach, right? The פסוק pasuk in ויקרא Vayikra
where it speaks about that says, right, וטבל הכהן את אצבעו מן
הדם והזה שבע פעמים לפני ה' את פני הפרוכת, v'taval hakohen et
etzba'o min hadam v'hizah sheva pe'amim lifnei Hashem et p'nei haparochet, ומן
הדם יתן על קרנות המזבח אשר לפני ה'. u'min hadam yitein al
karnos hamizbeach asher lifnei Hashem. So when he's putting the blood on
the horns, it says המזבח אשר לפני ה'. hamizbeach asher lifnei Hashem.
It didn't say that when he said he sprinkled on the פרוכת.
parochet. Nevertheless we learn out that the מזבח mizbeach is for the,
for not יום כיפור Yom Kippur but for the פר par of
כל המצוות, kol hamitzvos, the מזבח mizbeach is always לפני ה', lifnei
Hashem, he's always here. So even when he does the seven he
stands here and then he does it, but on יום כיפור Yom
Kippur he does the seven on the altar here and then he
comes out and he does the הזאה. haza'ah. Okay, that's ויצא. v'yatza.
Okay, הץ כמי מחטבי ויורה. hitz k'mi machtvei v'yorei. On יום כיפור
Yom Kippur he does the seven and the one standing here, right?
He does one and seven and then does another one and seven
for the פר, par, and then the שעיר, se'ir, right? And then
he, and then he mixes them, right, that's what we had, he,
they get mixed in one vessel, and he mixes it, right? And
then ויצא, v'yatza, and then he does this. But he's standing here
when he does the seven and one. Okay, and then it's ויצא
אל המזבח. v'yatza el hamizbeach. ויצא אל המזבח, v'yatza el hamizbeach, okay.
As opposed to by the other things he stands here, I mean
even on the מזבח, mizbeach, which by the way, besides the issue
of distance, you know, again emphasizing the greater intimacy and the greater
closeness that you get on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, it's important to
note that difference. Okay, yeah. So all this blood just goes through
the floor? And when they spill it out here? What? He says
there's a drain. Where is the drain on the inside? There is
no drain, but it was only a few drops, yeah. So that
doesn't make, no, that just stays until the, exactly. And all the
stuff they would pour, it's all the stuff they would pour on
the base, it's not the stuff they would put on the horns
up here didn't get mixed and that would stay on the horns.
I don't know if they would ever wash it. But there's a
drain in the base? Oh, yeah, but that's for the wine, that's
not for the blood. What? The inside מזבח. mizbeach. The blood is
just, yeah, I don't know if they would ever wash it. No,
no, no, he spills it out here. It says he comes out
here and he spills it on the יסוד הדרומי. yesod hadromi. He
pours it. Yeah. And that supposedly finds its, somehow there's a channel,
I don't know where the channel is, somehow, you know, it finds
its way here and then it goes out, right? Yeah. When he
was standing here, the east of the inner altar, the inner altar
of incense. Yes. Do you think, and he sprinkles towards the פרוכת,
parochet, do you think he's standing north or south of the altar
or do you think he's sprinkling right over the altar towards? Yeah,
I don't know. I really don't know. You mean by the other
thing, by the פר העלם דבר? par he'elam davar? Yes. Yeah, I
don't know. You had to pay for the water that from the
spring? We're learning that too. So how do they handle the water
that went into the יריחו? Yerecho? Right. They used it for fertilizer.
Drinking. Drinking. After it came out of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
after it had the sewage of the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? But
it would merge, it would get, I mean they use water, there
wasn't so much free water around. Yeah. I don't know. I imagine
that this wasn't the stream, that some water from the stream was
diverted here and then it became like a sewage pipe, but it
didn't mean that this was the whole stream. It's empty in נחל
קדרון. Nachal Kidron. It ends up in the, I understand, the sewage
pipe emptied, I don't understand the problem. הר הבית, Har Habayis, right?
Here's the sewage pipe, it enters into נחל קדרון, Nachal Kidron, everybody,
that's just the sewage. That doesn't mean that's the whole stream. Everybody
did that until about a hundred years. Anyway, I don't understand the
problem. I don't understand the problem. That's the sewage. That's the water
that was diverted for the sewage. It doesn't mean they had to
pay to drink that water. Yes, when it goes out to נחל
קדרון. Nachal Kidron. Excuse me, the end of the משנה Mishna is
it goes out to נחל קדרון, Nachal Kidron, there's a treasurer of
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash standing there collecting that and selling everything
that comes out to gardeners to use as fertilizer. That's what the
משנה Mishna says. In the middle of the desert when I want
to have a cup of water, I have to pay the treasurer
of בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash to drink water? He's also making money.
No, this is just what's the run-off of the sewage. It doesn't
go into the, he's saying it doesn't... נחל Nachal is a wadi.
נחל, Nachal, excuse me, נחל Nachal is a wadi, נחל Nachal is
not a river. נחל Nachal is a wadi, it is not a
river. I think that's the problem. We're not talking about it goes
into another water source. It's a flowing spring, right? No, it is
a sewage pipe that enters into a wadi, not into a water
source and that's the... sewage is collected and sold to gardeners. You're
saying נחל Nachal is a man-made? No, נחל Nachal is a wadi,
not a river. נחל קדרון Nachal Kidron does not have water flowing
through it all the year. But when it does? Okay, so apparently,
I don't know what would be when it had water flowing through
or something at the end of the sky. Yeah, exactly. That's caught
all the runoff from the מקדש Mikdash and then there was a
little guy with a table, measuring cups, and מאזניים moznayim and he
would like sell it to gardeners. Right. But yes, the difference, okay,
the lack of clarity was that the נחל Nachal was basically a
dry wadi. Okay, let's read a little bit more. תנו רבנן: Tanu
rabanan: התחיל מחצי היורד, hitchil mechatzi hayored, התחיל מחצי היורד, hitchil mechatzi
hayored, מהיכן היה מתחיל? meheichan hayah matchil? מקרן מזרחית דרומית, mikerren mizrachit
dromit, so south-east, דרומית מערבית, dromit maaravit, south-west, מערבית צפונית, maaravit tzonit,
north-west, צפונית מזרחית, tzonit mizrachit, north-east, דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei Rabbi Akiva.
So this is a different position. This starts in the south-east, okay,
so this position starts in the south-east, and then what would it
do after the south-east? דרומית מערבית, dromit maaravit, so then it would
go south-west. So this position would actually start here and rather than
this, which would go this way and start here, this position would
start in the south-east and go this way and it would go
in the opposite direction. Okay, so what is that debate going to
be? So let's just see if we can quickly see that. Okay,
דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei Rabbi Akiva. רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר: Rabbi Yose
HaGlili omer: מקרן מזרחית צפונית, mikerren mizrachit tzonit, no, he would start
north-east as we had said, צפונית מערבית, tzonit maaravit, he would go
counter-clockwise, north-west, מערבית דרומית, maaravit dromit, south-west, דרומית מזרחית, dromit mizrachit, south-east.
מקום שרבי יוסי הגלילי מתחיל, makom she-Rabbi Yose HaGlili matchil, where רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili would begin, שם רבי עקיבא פוסק, sham
Rabbi Akiva posek, that's where רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would end. Okay,
מקום שרבי עקיבא מתחיל, makom she-Rabbi Akiva matchil, where רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva would begin, שם רבי יוסי הגלילי פוסק. sham Rabbi Yose HaGlili
posek. Okay. So what is this about? So דכולי עלמא מהא בההוא
קרן דפגע ברישא לא עביד. de-kulei alma mi-ha be-hu kerren de-paga beresha
lo avid. Everybody agrees you did not start with the first corner
you hit because that would have been one of the ones on
the west, not the ones on the east. So מאי טעמא, mai
ta'ama, why? אמר שמואל דאמר קרא: amar Shmuel damar kra: ויצא אל
המזבח, veyatzah el hamizbe'ach, the exit to the altar. עד דנפיק מכולי
מזבח, ad denafik mikulei mizbe'ach, you have to be outside. Okay, so
now, fine, but that's how it's being read. ורבי עקיבא, ve-Rabbi Akiva,
now we have two questions. A, why does one north and one
south? And also why is one clockwise and one's counter-clockwise? So if
you remember we always assume counter-clockwise like we do here. So why
is רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva going clockwise? ורבי עקיבא ניקוף דרך ימין,
ve-Rabbi Akiva neikuf derech yamin, go counter-clockwise. So לימא ברמי בר יחזקאל
קמיפלגי. leima be-Rami bar Yechezkel kamifligi. Maybe they debate רמי בר יחזקאל.
Rami bar Yechezkel. דאמר רמי בר יחזקאל: damar Rami bar Yechezkel: ים
שעשה שלמה, yam sheasah Shlomo, the ים yam of שלמה, Shlomo, the
big מקווה mikveh that שלמה Shlomo had in the בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. So what does the פסוק pasuk say? עומד על שנים עשר
בקר, omed al shneim-asar bakar, was on these twelve figures of cattle,
like molten cattle. שלש פנים צפונה, shlosh panim tzonah, three north, שלש
פנים ימה, shlosh panim yamah, three west, שלש פנים נגבה, shlosh panim
negbah, three south, שלש פנים מזרחה, shlosh panim mizrachah, three east. So
if you think about it going from the north to the west,
that's your counter-clockwise movement. So that פסוק pasuk shows you counter-clockwise. והים
עליהם מלמעלה וכל אחוריהם ביתה. ve-hayam aleihem milma'alah ve-chol achoreihem baytah. And
the back, their תחתים tuchuses were all like inner, they were, you
know, their heads were facing outside. Fine. Okay. הא למדת, halamadta, from
there you learn שכל פינות שאתה פונה לא יהיו אלא דרך ימין
למזרח, shekol pinot sheata poneh lo yehu ela derech yamin lemizrach, that
you're always turning to the right and turning to the east. So
maybe this is debated? Maybe רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva doesn't believe in
the general idea of turn to the right, of counter-clockwise? No, yeah,
that's the purple line? No, yeah, that's clockwise. That's clockwise, that's counter-clockwise.
No, no, no, it's always seen as you're facing on the inside.
Yes. מר אית ליה דרמי בר יחזקאל, mar it lei de-Rami bar
Yechezkel, maybe one holds like רמי בר יחזקאל, Rami bar Yechezkel, ומר
לית ליה דרמי בר יחזקאל. umar leit lei de-Rami bar Yechezkel. Is
it possible that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva basically rejects the idea of
counter-clockwise? He says, no, no, דכולי עלמא אית להו דרמי בר יחזקאל.
dekulei alma it lehu de-Rami bar Yechezkel. Everybody agrees the general rule
is counter-clockwise. והכא בהא קמיפלגי: ve-hacha be-ha kamifligi: מר סבר ילפינן פנים
מחוץ, mar savar yalfinan panim mi-chutz, one assumption is do you say
what's true out in the עזרה, azarah, in the, you know, in
the עזרה azarah is true in the innermost sanctum, in the היכל.
Heichal. So yes, that's true outer in the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, the ים
של שלמה, Yam shel Shlomo, there it's counter-clockwise. Inside it's different, which
is bizarre. Why does the direction change? ומר סבר לא ילפינן פנים
מחוץ. umar savar lo yalfinan panim mi-chutz. Okay,
so that's one explanation. ורבי עקיבא, ve-Rabbi Akiva, says the גמרא, Gemara,
אי נמי דלא ילף פנים מחוץ i-nami de-lo yalaf panim mi-chutz fine,
you don't have to learn it from the outside. But אי בעי
הכי עביד
ואי בעי הכי עביד, i ba'ei hachi avid vei ba'ei hachi avid,
he
should at least be allowed to go counter-clockwise. If you could be
allowed to do either way, it sounds like he says דווקא davka
you have to do it clockwise. Why is that? So אמר לך
רבי עקיבא, amar lecha Rabbi Akiva, and with this we'll end, מדינא
בההוא קרן דפגע ברישא בו עביד ברישא. mi-dina be-hu kerren de-paga beresha
bu avid beresha. You should have started when you were walking out,
you should have started with the one you bumped into first. You
just the הלכה halakha was you had to go to the outside,
but this was the first one you encountered. Okay, דאמר ריש לקיש
de-amar Reish Lakish אין מעבירין על המצוות, ein ma'avirin al ha-mitzvot, you're
not supposed to pass by an opportunity to do a מצוה. mitzvah.
ואמאי לא עביד, ve-amai lo avid, why did he not start this
corner, which is the one you hit first? משום דכתיב mishum de-chsiv
ויצא אל המזבח ve-yatza el ha-mizbe'ach that you have to go out
עד דנפיק מכולה מזבח. ad de-nafik mikulei mizbe'ach. וכיון דיהיב בההוא קרן,
ve-keivan de-yahiv be-hahu keren, הדר אתי לההוא קרן דחייב למיסב ברישא. hadar
asi le-hahu keren de-chayiv lemisav be-reisha. So since this is the first
one you encountered, you're forced to go out, you're forced to start
here, but the next place you should be going is back to
the place that you missed. Now by the way, for רבי יוסי
הגלילי Rebbe Yosi Ha-Gelili it also works, because since he's saying you
do it in the north, you bump into this, you don't do
it, you start here, but then you go back to the one
you missed. So for רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbe Yosi Ha-Gelili he can
go immediately back to the one he missed and go the standard
counterclockwise. But for רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva that has you in the
south, to be going back to the one you missed has you
going in the clockwise direction. So the only debate we have to
figure out now is not clockwise versus counterclockwise, that we get, you're
going back to the one you missed, but why one of them
starts in the north and one of them starts in the south,
so we will see that tomorrow. How do we explain תני tani